hi all good evening how's everyone doing how's your weekend going guys?
okay so did anyone try that flex froggy that I pinged you last week I mean last
class did anyone practice on that let me pin that that's like a weekday okay
Abhishek you're planning you're doing some assignments or stuff like how's
the day was going just randomly watching some content consuming it Abhishek so
guys we'll wait for two three minutes then we'll get started let me share my
screen okay office work where do you work Abhishek if you don't mind
I check all our days too okay does my screen share is working guys can give me
thumbs up if screen share is working fine right let's say we have a three
minutes timer get started okay push the I pushed it Munesh like you could have
reminded me in the whatsapp I would have done that I just seen that some code
was pending so I couldn't push it just I just have done that nobody I'm happy at
the place where I am so how's your experience at Acolyte Digital yeah
but why on weekends is it like work life balance is wrong or like there's
something going on crazy yeah can someone share the whatsapp group link
guys okay old tech what tech you're working on we could have chatted on this
like in a normal way also to your opinion personally saw all other doesn't
for to see never been near and on that Abhishek never been around that for
currency see I have learned it some for some time but not to that like photon
level so guys how many of you have solved the assignments of previous
class or how many face challenge or anyone having any challenges is those
assignments easy enough great age I see only six votes guys can anyone
have ping in the whatsapp group again like we are getting started easy and
basic great I see less people join class today that's the reason someone can
will get started I specifically put a message such that you know this this is
of today's a weekend right so people are indifferent okay that's why I was like
there was only one question in assignment but I have shared I've shared
flex froggy to practice you can check in the pinned one that that would be
really helpful you know to practice it it's very difficult to get a job in a
full stack as a fresher it's tricky because freshers you know there are two
different domains one is SD roles had good good companies where you are
expected to perform in certain role then it's fine but there are some companies
which you consider yourself as a fresher as a fresher whatever skill set your
position poses doesn't matter to them they train you against on something what
they wanted so either of it but I would prefer like you pick something open
source related tech and then go into that let's get started guys okay what do
you think react is going to replace with next year's next year's is a react
framework you cannot build next year's project without using react do you think
it you can do it Abhishek next year next year's is just you know I'll come to
that actually I'll actually come to that what is react and what is next year's
well I'll just introduce next year's because I wouldn't think you know really
bigger enterprise applications right are still using next year's we haven't
moved it our application is not on next year's because we are analyzing state
performances and everything if we want to move it on to that or not okay
so guys we'll talk about that in future in summit let's come back to today's
class we'll get started yeah so guys in last class we'll discuss something
called as flexbox can anyone can all of you define in your own terms what is
flexbox actually what did you understood by this one just I'm having a recap of
what we have learned in last class can anyone give me what do they understand
this by the word flexbox any keyword that you have
okay so Kiran says for layout okay auto layout as per screens right yeah
layout can we say this is as a flexible box box for cross screen development
songs cross-screen layouts like multi-screen layouts like whatever it is
right yeah to build a responsive website as per screen dimension right so yeah we
have understood this one now the second question that I want to ask with a
flexbox is a one-direction layout or two-direction layout
guys it's one direction it's not two direction people who have you know
replying me 2d I'll talk on that I haven't I've told her it's a one
direction the reason you arrange only items depending on flex direction right
and flex direction can be either row or column only one direction isn't it either
you pick it up yeah so you are putting all your items either in row or in
column and depending on that you are moving that items right now when I put
row what would be the main axis case when I put flex direction as a row what
could be the main axis X and cross axis would be y ultimately similarly vice
versa right now when I'm considering let's say I'm considering row as an
example what does justify
content us
what does justify content as us give it for give it to us
quick guys quick justify content spread end-to-end but on which direction on
which direction on main axis or cross axis
so it helps us to move the elements on a main axis right
move items on main axis then when it comes to align items
you
you guys I'm audible
I think my had a network connection I got stuck in between I had to connect
with my mobile hotspot pardon me for that but again okay let's get back to
this one guys now after justify content and align items we learned one of the
one more property which is used to you know stop overflowing of elements into
the one single line such that you know as we move the screen width and width it
pushes the other items to the below of wrap right yeah flex wrap so so we used
to wrap all the items such that you know those take whatever space is needed and
push the other items to the below right then we understood another property
called a line content like you are if you have flexible container whatever
container you have defined it if it's a larger in size and all the elements are
being fitted in only top like let's say you have three four elements there is
enough space to move all this other items if you want to move anywhere those
all content right on the in that container you can use a line content
again move all items inside container right these are the properties that we
discussed on a container specific like any property that you remember guys on
children elements on items on child items right so can I say order in if you
want to change the order of particular like rendering process like if you want
to move the element from two to three three to one right order then you had a
sorry flex grow like if you are increasing the screen width how the item
should particularly you know react to it like how much by in which ratio it
should grow then we used flex should grow and similarly for the opposite we
use flexing like if a red is in the screen width how that particular item
should behave then we had like a flex basis which was acting like a maximum
maximum width a product that particular item can take right so these are the
things that we have learned already in the last class so how many of you are
feeling comfortable or you know feeling better of this properties because
everything you would see that comes with a practice like it will take time so
that you be good with them it will take time but at least by definition and by
yes you know whatever I have tried to explain so you if you are able to
understand this one please give me thumbs up and we can go ahead with the
great part today if anyone have doubt on flex layout or using a display as flex
drop me a question we'll take it up in the doubt session okay now let's get
started with great guys let's get started with great
okay now how many of you remember are this one matchbooks where we were
supposed to write one two three initially in our childhood it used to
look like this one isn't it okay no worries I just tried to revise it but
you will be able to feel comfortable once you watch the session okay but how
many of you remember this book guys which had boxes and used to fill in one
two three four right so grid also works in a same way where earlier when we
talked or discussed about flex right we thought in terms of X and Y axis and we
were aligning items along X axis either or along Y axis but here this is not the
case here you can define how many rows and how many columns you want like same
way how we define an array when you initialize an array you're supposed to
give the rows and columns isn't it like you provide maybe three rows and four
columns right but when it comes to CSS you also have to define many properties
like width height and all other things we'll see how we can leverage this
layout and build really complex one in a very easy format so I don't really have
anything to say on theory part but it's just a 2d layout where you can always
configure items on rows and column because you have an ability to deal on
change those things okay we'll see more on a practical basis like how this thing
works let's go and start with the directly visual studio code
I'll start as a class 6 let's say we have one index start HTML so firstly I'll
try to set up a basic layout guys such that we can get started with actual grid
right but till then whatever code I'm writing if you feel any challenge in
that also right help me out understanding a problem I'll try to
answer that okay so let's say I say this is a good now inside body let's say what
I'll do is now I'll show you some of the shortcuts guys like m8 one what I'll do
is that I'll say def dot container okay once I have this and I click enter now
just see whenever I use dot operator what does it mean in HTML files what do
we exactly mean when we say dot operator class right let's say now I'm
clicking enter it has built a div with this class as a container so I don't
need to type down every the HTML element so you can leverage Emmet to do this
okay now let's say I go and build something like def okay and I say item
and I multiply it by 9 now what I'm saying that created a with item class
and nine times so when I click enter it has built me this night now what I'll do
I'll just you know type down all the numbers so that we can create these
boxes
okay once we have this now let's go to style let's explore open this in preview
right we are having them all in a one line since all the items are block in
nature okay once again this is Emmet abbreviation Emmet shortcuts guys so just
I'm using whatever element you have and then you can use hash for IT or dot for
your class and that's I'm using item one when I do item one and click enter it
will be they will be created with it's an automatic if okay
now let's go and create style block inside style block first they will give
some basic properties to the container before coming into the container now I
if you see here I'm having here space on the top on the left side I see some of
the padding how can we remove this guys how can we remove this because there's
something coming by default right we have to say that whatever padding or
match margin by default div is having I want to override it with 0 0 let's say
I say 0 and padding as 0 see now those are aligned to the start of the page
right next I'll go and define some CSS in the for the body type whole items
whichever present in the body I'm assigning to them okay now what all
things I'll apply so let's say we make like just trying to increase the font
size I say 20 pixel of each number whatever content is there in the whole
page then how many of you remember line height
line height do you remember line height
right so let's say if I give 1.5 what just happened for each line it just took
1.5 times of height right like increasing it for text ankit I think I
already had it in class for when you go for font text I've used here this line
height you can explore this one it will be there already okay like what is it
exactly like if you have a paragraph how much each line should be a half height
off so that's our basic different basic definition then let's say I use a color
as a dodger blue so what I did is like I just converted this color now let's say
I give some background color as a tomato okay looking really odd but will make it
look good now coming back to this one container okay so here where we learn
all the things but before coming to this one let's let's keep do something let's
give some width to the container as of now let's say 600 pixel and let's say
height is somewhere around 550 pixel once we have this height and width yeah
right yeah 1.5 times of font size 1.5 times okay now let's say I have a
border of 2 pixel solid black
okay and let's say I also give some margin to it by default I say 100 pixel
right now I say that auto okay now is what do you think this is when I say
auto or do you think exactly what I'm trying to do here I'm just introduce
this one I'll overwrite this one but whenever I'm using somewhere or to what
does it exactly like do you feel like when if I even if I'm increasing
yep I mean it will try to give depending on right let's say exact screen width it
will automatically calculate how much you need it let's say I if I explore
open this if I open in the live server I'll show you this how this one works
not exactly center but if you see
no
if I select this and if I go for you know margin inside container if you see
it's 267 if I keep extending it is automatically cali calculating and
putting it in the center so among as you said it is right only but auto adjust
automatically it will calculate such that all the items are in center is it
okay guys it's just like flexible one like as as soon as you increase doesn't
matter but it will put items into the center okay now once the margin is done
like what's next is what's next an item that we can add here by default can we
some padding okay I'll get I'll explain that copy so if you see here I am
selecting container and by default I've give margin a top and bottom as 100 but
the other margin I kept it as auto currently it shows 453 pixel but if I
keep decreasing okay up to an extent okay it up to an extent now what is an
extent is like till that width is hit okay till that width is hit but if I
increasing over the width on to the top of it how however you increase it
doesn't matter it will distribute the equal amount of margins above 550 pixel
of width like we since we have defined with the 600 pixel now if you are
increasing the screen width now if you see a screen with this 1220 it will do
1220 minus 600 and whatever is remaining it will distribute it and put that
particular container in the center
it won't take whole size of L&R left and right yeah it is taking if you see yeah
it will put it in center auto is like just like calculating whatever left and
right you want you distribute on yourself
did you get this point okay now moving ahead once we added padding let me open
this up it let's say I give width I reduce this 500 of width or 450 pixel of
width just to see this one okay now going next next race now earlier if I
used to do display and as soon as I give flex do you see would you what would
happen guys what is expected to happen if I give
display as a flex
yes if I apply display as flex as of here what is supposed to happen on the
container level yeah all items will move in the row right let's let's just let's
let's see okay all the items are moving in a row as suggested but before coming
to this display property let's add some margins and borders to this each item
okay each item let's give some basic styles let's say I select item and let's
say background color I would give it like again for this one also I'll give
as a dodger blue but will override color property that we defined a bow as smoke
white
sorry white smoke okay then I'll give something like a border one pixel solid
black then we'll give some like padding eight pixel that's okay now if I give
again let's say as a flex it is supposed to move all the elements and it is
consuming all the height okay but now let's say if I give it as a grid let's
see what's happening by default when you apply the grid there is no chain isn't
it these are block level elements and they're supposed to be render this way
and these are rendered in such in such format itself isn't it right so by
default when it's not a directional base it is a 2d direction so by the
until unless you go and do the formatting there's nothing being
applied here okay once if you do it here how can you play around with the 2d
format like how can you define number of rows into number of columns that's where
we are going to enter now let's say if I go with grid template columns now
inside template columns I can say that how many columns I need firstly for
that let's say I say that I need hundred pixel one then let's say I need hundred
pixel two and then also I need another hundred pixel three now what I just say
it here what I defined it here is that I've created a display of a grid
format then I told that I need three columns now how many ever you
define here you have to define each column and its respective height size
okay column whatever width is there okay what we have done we have created three
columns and we gave each column as a hundred pixel now if I create again add
a hundred pixel the fourth column will be created is this clear like how this
is working first template grid template columns guys how many of you understood
this one if there is someone who didn't understand can they can give me
thumbs down okay I hope this point is clear like this this is how you define
columns like when we thought about an array also or a grid format you always
deals with the rows and columns I'm trying to show like if you want to create
a column this is how you do it specifying each particular column like
number of columns individually like that pattern okay now there are many ways
that you can define this way let's say you can give 25 pixel 25 sorry percentage
and then 25 percentage okay then again 25% so it accepts all the units that you
generally see even there's a new unit that I want to introduce something
called as VW okay does anyone know what is VW
height is we have given already right for container we have defined it but I'll
tell you I'll come to that I'll come to that view width okay viewport width
generally so we are saying that does 25% and viewport width is equal
no right so but even if I yeah exactly so it's not but I was just trying to
show you that all it accepts all the units so we'll go with the percentages
but this is fine but what if I have the grid specifically gives us a one of the
better way to describe how the element should be distributed and this is the
one of the industry standard how they distributed like let's say if I use a
word like 1fr okay then I say that 2fr let's say 2fr then I say again 1fr okay
what do I exactly mean by this 1fr or 2fr 1fr fr goes for frame rate okay now
how this is calculated how this is calculated let's go let me save this
let's go to here let's come here now if you see here what what's happening here
okay what I'll select something this element selector let's remove the as of
now responsive layer okay if I go and select this one and apply on the
container item level one item one right what is the width and height of it okay
what is the width and height of it guys if I increase this nothing is applying
but I'm getting us 94 pixel nothing is affected here till you click enter but
what can you see here what is the width and height of this particular element
let's say if I select item 2 it's it's w into h guys 165 is a height 207 is
width right now if I go for item 3 it is still showing 94 okay now coming this
is just a mathematical definition here like if I write down let's say your whole
container width okay let's say if I define how I can say that is that what
is the container width guys here 450 pixel right can you see here container
width is 450 pixel now this container pixel is divided by whole summation of
frame rates how many frame rates we have here if I sum them 4 right now let's say
if I have four some rates what could be the each some rate each frame rate
value
right 1 to 1 point 1 to 1 to 0.5 right now so what happens here what happens
here is that whenever you are giving in frame rates what it divides is what it
does is like it takes a whole width and it do the mathematical equation before
the behind the scenes and each column now let's say when you select one FR it
will have width of 1 to 1.5 okay now let's go back and see do we have 1 to
well point width now if I select item 2 let's item 3 now 94 plus a like if you
calculate 8 what could be the unit let's say 16 like if you calculate this one
right 16 plus 2 18 right width padding is 8 plus 8 16 plus 2 18 plus 94 are you
getting that 1 to l point 5 right so if you calculate this one so that is what
here we are getting it now whenever you say one frame rate how comes 18 guys
padding is also considered into width right when we are using here we didn't
use box a border box I mean box sizing if I use box sizing as a border box then
you will be able to see exact frame rate right that's what we learned right sorry
here it got reduced now if you use calculate this one do I need to do the
sum also let's say write down this let's say we are getting the height of this
box as 88 just let me write down somewhere here only 88 plus 16 what is
the sum guys 88 plus 16 94 plus 8 102 104 104 point 104 only now so what what I'm
supposed to explain I'm trying to explain here is that whenever you are
dealing in terms of frame rates whenever you are dealing in terms of frame rate
right that generally width whatever width you get it by default okay whatever
width you are getting it by default is equivalent to your total width of a
container divided by total frame rates is that point clear like how each
column is getting this width or how it is being calculated is that point clear
guys what we exactly mean by frame rate and how it can be calculated let's say
if I if I reduce it right let's say we have a 4 right let's say I reduce it to
100 now 400 the calculation becomes simple now let's say it becomes 400
divided by 4 which is equivalent to 100 right now let's say going back and
refreshing this one we select item 1 and go here and see this so if you see 82
plus 16 plus 2 which is 100 right
right so we when we give this exact unit right which can be divided by exact I
mean if you have a right value which which are when you are dividing by the
frame rates if you're getting it 0 it you will get an exact distribution but
if you have something like other pixels then you have somewhat here and there
but I hope you got the basic understanding like how the frame rates
are decided and what the value get it is that clear guys okay now anyone having
any doubt on the frame rate is every FR is clear if anyone is having still
challenge can I can have some can't we fix flex along with the column size
sorry I didn't flex and grid template column shunt firstly grid template
columns this particular property is only applied when display is grid now you can
be only apply flex to the display and once you apply display as a flex then
you have a separate properties which can you use to move the items here and there
using those list of properties that we just introduced when we are doing a
recap okay but to answer your question you you may you wouldn't be able to do
that here okay so once the frame rates are clear now guys this there are few
reusable functions that you can use it okay let me come to them let's say one
function is called as repeat now what repeat does is like repeat is generally
because if you if you see this let's say you have a website I didn't under I
didn't understand for okay okay so what I let's say I make it this as a 450
itself okay now I made as a 450 now what I did is like once I have a 450 width
now and I'm dividing total frame rates are by 4 each frame rate is supposed to
be 1 to l 0.5 of pixel how come 4 will be there like 1 plus 2 plus 1 3 plus 1
4 because I am using 4 free like a first some of 4 3fr like all their first is
that clear among like what is the sum of yeah like I am calculating this like
sum of all these elements like 1fr plus let's say what is this sum right or
let's let me write down here that 4 also how I'm getting 1fr plus 2fr plus 1fr
that's how we have been able to utilize it for easier calculations I am giving
400 pixel now coming back to this one guys what does repeat does now if you go
for a website site most of the times what happens is like you don't have
really like too many columns or how do you define it or if there is something
that all the columns are of same size like a table format if you see in the
most of the tables you have a equal sized columns for those use cases what
you can do is that you can use a repeat function what does repeat function takes
is that it takes two value it says that hey can you give me a number of columns
you need and the width of each column okay once you keep this function and call
it it is supposed to return its returns is this in this format let's say if I
give it like repeat I say give me three columns of 1fr each okay so what it will
return is here at runtime it will return what it what it does is like it
creates like 1fr 1fr and 1fr this is how it works behind the scenes no so I'll
just show you the exact like like how you can leverage it let's say I go and
write a repeat function inside that I give that one like three columns and I
say that 1fr let's say for calculation specific I'll use 4 where you will be
able to see 100 pixel because with this 400 pixel okay so you are creating four
columns each one of one frame rate by if you go by calculation you are supposed
to have hundred pixel each column right let's say we go and see it here on the
item one you calculate 82 plus again the same padding and this one okay is this
clear guys what does repeat does for us if R is a fractional unit yeah sorry let
me check the definition of it give me a second
yeah fractional unit you can say that but we can't use if you want a different
fr right if you want different as fr then we cannot use this repeat function
okay I'll write down this fractional unit so repeat can be only used when you
want to replicate same like same width let's say even not fr in terms of let's
say you want a hundred pixel one also okay or let's say you want a ten pixel
one also it's up to you whatever you can define but if you want like only to
repeat the columns then only you go for this one is that clear guys like what
went to use repeat and what is the use case of repeat is okay great now once
this is clear now then there are few things guys that I want to explain now
if you see here let's go and let's save this and let's see like what what's
happening here if I go for increase and decrease this one there wouldn't be
nothing happening because I'm not playing around with a container but I'm
playing around with this one okay but what I wanted to show you is that let's
say I have fixed the size of hundred pixel what if we want this to be act
like a flexible thing like if you want to give a range of values like where it
can take let's say now if you see even if I'm reducing it it is still like
reducing in an equivalent size but what if we want to give them a variable size
like a range of values for that also grid has given us a function which is
called as min max okay min max what does min max does is it takes two values
again where you can define it like what could be the minimum value and maximum
let's say you have 80 pixel to 1 fr okay or else let's say 50 pixel there's
nothing changed here nothing changed as of now right but what we are saying is
that let's say but I'll show that when this thing will change but is the
definition of min max is clear like we are saying that whatever columns you are
creating the column size can be anything between 50 pixel to 1 fr which is like
100 pixel so there where it can vary from that to that range okay now once
this is done now what if we don't know right we never know that like the number
of columns will be always consistent like what if we want like some property
like flex wrap like what if like there is a space more space coming up and the
instead of going on a second row like 5 6 7 and it can accommodate here itself
right that sort of it should be we should be it should be able to take that
right like something like flex wrap like let's say if I'm increasing the
space let's say I increase the space
since I'm having a 1fr it is automatically will work fine but let's
say I make it as a hundred pixel okay now I make this width as a let's say 700
pixel now if you see there's enough space here do you see this enough space
on the right let's say I go to chrome there's a space but this space is wasted
right in a grid layer we want the space to be consumed isn't it what if we had
a flex wrap like it would have or took all the elements and if there is not
enough space only then it would have pushed to the next row right
yes if is anyone able to relate this right so for that reasons right what flex
or a grid team has done they have given us two values so if you are not sure of
about like let's say we told like firstly we'll define each column size okay what
if the column size always keep changing then we told that you can give a range
of values minimum maximum such that your fixed column size has become variable
now that it can range from here to here similarly what if we can make columns
also variable like it can do anything let's say for those things what grid
team has done is they have introduced two properties one is called autofill
and the other one is autofill
just let me check the convention guys
yeah I think this is it
okay now if you see what just happened if I go back again if you see this
autofill aligned all the elements in single like in one row we see only one
particular column isn't it now just let me check this autofill it shouldn't be
this convention yeah this one actually this is how it works if you see on the
container right what we have done we have told that of like if you see the
of this grid template we show we told that repeat all the columns autofill
the space if you have whatever space you have fill the each color take as many
columns you can take it and each column width whatever width can be it can be
ranged from 50 pixel to 100 pixel okay and what it does is that clear like how
this is working guys we are saying to repeat now as many columns you can fill
it as much you can fill it in a one row and each column can take between 50 to
100 now let's say what is the width of each box let's say what is the width of
each box now it's a still it is hundred no let's say if I try to reduce it if I
try to reduce the container with let's say if I'm trying to reduce it okay if
it is not able to accommodate new new party it will throw into the second row
like same as a flex wrap let's say I'm reducing it below 600 where maximum is
like 100 pixel what we have given if it comes below that the sixth element will
go down if I reduce below 500 for fifth element will also come down let's say if
I go below this now is this clear like how autofill is working if there is a
space available let's say if I make 900 pixel all the rows will be applied on a
same row itself like autofill is like trying to fill as many as elements can
come into the same row with this particular value minimum and maximum
okay
guys is autofill clear
anyone having any doubts till now whatever we have discussed anyone
having any doubts okay right now then there is something is that I want to
show you something called as autofit
now let's go back and see the see the property how it is behaving now I had
700 pixel I'll just reduce it okay do you see any change here do you see any
change here between autofill what if we give a thousand pixel give it thousand
hundred pixel not hundred pixel but a thousand pixel right all the properties
took their value and and you know are coming in one row is that clear like it
will consume a whole row and extra hundred pixel right with there you can
still give a new element if there is a new element it will consume it okay now
guys do you see any difference between autofit and autofill now I mean do you
feel anything till now like even if I'm reducing increasing still autofill and
autofit are working like a same right right they both are working like same
but now what does autofit does what does autofit does I'll show you
let's say I give it unit instead of fixed value since I'm using 50 pixel to
100 pixel it is supposed to take only 100 pixel as a maximum and these are
rendered as a hundred pixel space that's I use this hundred pixel because I can
show you exactly like how all the kind like elements are being moved to the
top bottom or the top but now let's say I go and give it as a fr here instead of
min and max I give it as a fr no what just happened what just happened is
think of it like why like what could be the value of one fr could come is by
default we say that seven hundred divided by one so it is consuming whole
space and all the elements are coming in one row but let's say I give one of the
value just let me take this okay
let's say we take this as this one where I'm trying to repeat autofitted and I'm
using min max
ranging from hundred pixel to one fr okay and let's say I'm having this 700
columns now let's go back here and see the some difference if there is some
difference happening if I increase reduce the space still there is no does
it look like any difference guys still
I got one answer but I want some other people to notice it
there's only one thing guys let's say I make it let's say instead of autofit I
give fi LL just observe if I'm reducing it if I'm increasing it I'm reducing
below 600
let's say instead of this one we'll give something like 80 to view this one instead
of one fr it will take in units only but let me show you yeah zoom in zoom out
okay let me show you one of the thing like a video which will show you exactly
difference between autofill and autofit to visualize this one better so what
happens is generally if you see like there are seven elements there are seven
elements okay and you have given some range like let's say you are even in the
yeah shrinking shrinking and expanding is becoming automatically I'll if you
see this example when I'm making it autofit the elements inside it whatever
elements you see inside that they shrink and you know increase in size if you see
the width of them are increasing according to this range okay if I what
was happening is earlier when I had a fill when I let's say I have a fill
again we were able to see the spaces in that right empty spaces in a row let's
say if I increase this one as a thousand pixel again if you see there is a space
but what if I make as a fit this is the difference so we had thousand pixel of
width so it can accommodate 10 items in it isn't it it can accommodate 10 items
of 100 pixel but we told that hey autofitted like you can take the space
each column width from 80 pixel to the 1fr unit now 1fr will come but
like when you divide a thousand pixel divided by one like 1fr if I convert
into this one same thing into fill now let's say if you see this what what
just happened where is the width guys did I lost width let me refresh this one
I have width now I have autofill instead of autofit let's have autofill
as of now firstly and let's make thousand pixel so firstly I'll tell you
what just happened in this what is what is this example is talking about let's
go to the container now what we just told is that hey you have width of
thousand pixel and also make this as a 80 min minimum as 80 doesn't matter
though but I'll just show you the difference
let's say I make it autofill firstly and I make as a thousand pixel of width so
now guys can you see the firstly space on the right side can you see the spaces
on the first right side on the on this right side so what does autofill does it
firstly there are two things that are happening when you use autofill or
autowrite so they check like if they can accommodate extra column they keep on
adding that extra column okay they keep on adding whatever columns they can
accommodate but if there is a more width left autofill leave that space as
an empty space empty column but what does autofill does it it tries to
consume whole space fit the screen into that container
let's say if I give fit do you see that it is trying to consume whole space and
it is happening only because we are saying that the range exists from 0 80
pixel to 1fr now whenever we are giving a maximum as 1fr at runtime it will say
that hey like thousand pixel divided by 9 column it will come up to like 110
maybe right then it will distribute to the size of 110 for each item is this
difference clear between autofill and autofit autofit tries to accommodate as
many columns as it can in a one row plus if there are no columns are available it
tries to consume whole space rather than not leaving empty space around on the
right side or the left side is this point clear guys what is the
difference between autofill and autofit
or anyone having still challenge do let me know if anyone is still having
challenge do let me know so I hope this point is clear I'll try to write down
these definitions of this one using min max use it yeah is still using in min
max right so how that if you see that container with the right now if you go
and see the container each one it is above 80 pixel we told that each
item which should be around 80 to 1fr isn't it so it is taking that range it is
more than 80 pixel of each column says okay no going back to here let me write
down few definitions for min max it takes the range as a variable for column
or the row width okay now then we had discussed two other points autofill and
autofill and autofit sorry it tries to accommodate as many columns as it can
if columns are more than width width of container new columns will be moved to
into new row and if width of container is more than number of columns autofill
will leave empty space whereas autofit will adjust width according to
min max value min max range so I hope guys whatever we have discussed till now
how is the range to 110 pixel okay Kiran let me go back to this one so when my
width is thousand pixel and I the number of rows I have nine what could be the
one fractional unit value like you divide one 9fr divided by thousand right I mean
thousand divided by 9fr that's how it is coming nearby to 110 or 1 to whatever
calculation you can do let me yeah okay got it so guys is this clear what is how
FR is calculated how repeat function can be used or min max autofill auto write so
everything is a variable in grid like like we don't need to define any time of fixed values
like fixed units there's nothing like needed like you want to define anywhere fixed units so
you can everything you give you can give in range and you can give it auto auto fill or
repeat anything that you want but now for making our job easy I'll just give something like repeat
so that we can keep learning ahead with other properties I'll just give three columns with
and making this as a let's say 300 pixel for understanding it better okay now after as as we
have discussed for grid column now what if we want to give a gap between each column right so
let's say you have a if you want to give a gap you all you have something properties like column
gap if you give a column gap like let's say 10 pixel can see this there is a gap coming up
between each of the column so this can be also added similarly also have a property called row
gap let's say I also give this 10 pixel so there is a equal distribution that you can give whatever
gap you need between the items elements like items defined inside the container you can define it
here itself also if you want to give it as a common value right in like you can give 10
pixel and 8 pixel okay this again goes for same way guys let's say I comment this now like column
it comes as a let's say it takes value column then row I hope this property is also clear like
how does gap property works between the items pretty simple right straightforward now let's
say I go and calculate template rows now I'm going for rows like this is where today format
comes in let's I go and say repeat three like make it fix it into three columns because we
have only nine elements and I say instead of let's say one let's say I give one effort let's see what
happened here there's no change coming up but let's say we make 50 pixel can you see this
so this is where 2d layouts comes in earlier we were able to only align items according to
row or column but here we are saying number of columns we want number of rows we want let's
say I say that I need only two rows two rows repeat the two rows with a 50 pixel like first
two rows are with 50 pixel and the third row is consuming whatever width is available by default
is that clear like if it is if it need not to be always n by n or like that sort of parameter
you can give it anything even if you if you wanted like you can give individual descriptions
as we discussed earlier like 1fr then 2fr then 1fr again it's up to you yeah it is actually
height Raja because column goes for width right element width this is for height row height okay
now same properties all the properties that we learned or can be applied here also so I'm
just trying to repeat that repeat three columns with a 1fr I hope this point is clear guys
VH right I didn't get open Raya point so I make this to a view height not exactly view height
like this is a height of VH is a viewport height yeah no their height is not viewport height this
is like particular all the items whatever items you are getting we are again calculating FR is
again calculated by considering now we considered width right earlier now this will be calculated
depending on the height this will be divided like 550 divided by 3 and that height will come okay I
hope guys that point is clear like how this FR will be calculated for rows and how FR will be
calculated for columns so keep that difference like some way stay someone is taking width someone
is taking height to define it now going to the next property I hope this point is clear the
properties that you see in flex they are still applicable here properties like just a justify
items if I give justify items let's say I give it as a center and also let's say I give something
like align items center so now tell me there's this one what's exactly happening here what's
what happened what just happened here what does item when I'm trying to you know giving this
properties whatever property is applicable for flex let's say I give flex start for a better
interpretation now when I'm moving this item where these items are able to move where these
items are able to so each item is got some column height and column width right some column height
and like particular that box that grid box inside that grid box only if you want to rotate or move
anywhere this all the items you can use justify items and align items are you able to relate like
if I say whenever you go with this keyword here items you are trying to move items inside one cell
of grid is it relatable guys no like if I say center and center if I remove this property if
I comment this property if you say this is the cell if this is the whole cell and inside this
cell only I'm trying to move the item anywhere that I want to like I can move it to this corner
and this corner and this center so I am saying that you are trying to move the items inside one
cell of a grid or each cell with respect to itself like inside that particular cell this one will
revolve here two will be all revolving inside this particular thing is it relatable guys are
you able to understand this one this property how justify and align items are working here is anyone
having challenge understanding this property yes please give me thumbs up or thumbs down I'll try
to repeat it again because that's how I am able to understand it if you are not able to understand
when I ask it give me thumbs down I'll repeat it again yeah here items are not exactly digits if
you see I have each diff right yeah items are the digits but each diff boxes I've given them a
particular class and if you see when I say container I'm talking about this container this
border right if I go for the iPad right so just a second if you see we had one container
right inside container we distributed items or these bigger items this is a space each item
got it by default when we defined grid template rows and columns but inside this if we want to
say let's say this item is smaller enough and we want to move it here or here here here here
anywhere like and this item will be able to move here and here and here and here if you want to
move it to center you can also do that and to move this one you have to again move along the
y-axis inside the each element right justify content again goes for x-axis so justify item
and align item goes for y-axis okay inside that particular cell only if you want to move the
particular thing then you can use this property like you are not moving anywhere around the whole
grid or anywhere it will based on item length and like here it is one yeah right if I even
give lorem let's say lorem let's say not even if I try to update with two keywords if you see lorem
if some has content whatever content you have if you want to move that content let's say it's a
flex start as of now if I make them center center now imagine I give them center and also I make
them center so whatever cell that particular cell is having space it will move into that
particular respective things okay I hope this I this part of this whenever I'm using justify
so that it will be aligned to top left or right center bottom within that cell right
you got it clearly so within that cell only it will keep on moving when you're using with
items justify item and justify sorry align items but now you also want to move this items let's
say here what if I have let's say I go and make a container pretty big but how can I make a pretty
big container let's say let's say I give it the row as a 50 pixel each okay now if you see we
have this can we change for each item differently justify an align item I'll show that I'll show
that Raja you can do that but I'll show that but you have to if you have to do it for one one item
you have to go from the item level not from the container level currently all the properties
we are applying are on the container okay now guys if you see this there are the items inside
the container are on the top what if we want to move let's say this is a whole cell now this box
whatever this box if you want to move inside this container like somewhere bottom down or anywhere
left right how we can do that let's say I also make this as a 50 pixel instead of this one you
see now this will this like moving all the children items together inside a container all
items together you can do that using something property called as justify content all the
content all the content okay let's say I'm moving it to center if you see it got into center if I'm
moving again align content into the center it will bring all the items into the center
is it relatable guys how items and content are different when you are talking about content it
is you are talking about all the content when you're talking about items you're talking about
one respective item inside that cell is that difference clear guys when to go for items when
to go for content content is you are let's say you are trying to move item inside grid container
okay I hope the basic difference is clear when to use this properties in that properties but
there is some new property guy that the guys that I want to introduce something called as
place content like this is a short format same like you want to go for justify align content
and it starts like this way let's say I make it sent start and center so what does exactly it
is doing what does it is exactly doing let's say I comment this if I want to replicate the
start and center right I can say align content start same thing a shortcut for both things
like it goes place content goes with a line content then space justify content
too many things
let me recheck
is this clear guys how you can use a shortcut because whatever you are whenever you are
selecting place content so firstly you have to give what is a property of align content then
you have to give justify content property you can define individually but also you can give
in short format same goes with this align items okay let's say you want to do it for the align
items how can you do it now let's say I go for place items now what if I do center and center
so inside each cell they are again moving into the center and the syntax is same
like instead of content I'll use item here
is this clear guys what how you can leverage justify items justify content the basic difference
between those elements I hope this is clear if these points are clear then there is one more
property that I want to talk about let's say I fix this one again as a 1fr 1fr
okay now I wanted to observe some changes when I write down this property grid auto flows
I make it as column okay now again let's make it 50 pixel only as of now okay
any change did you guys observe let's say let's say I comment this shant has mentioned one thing
guys just see the numbering format just see the numbering format and if I uncomment it again
transfers right like 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 it was but it converted to 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
did you guys notice that
did you guys notice that so what this grid autoflow says grid autoflow says that let's say
whenever you are building a layout whenever you are building a layout
whatever first item when you add it is of course it will go to the top left according to the
column and road definition then it is always your decision like let's say
I write down here
let's say you have defined a grid of three by three matrix like okay where you have three
columns of 1fr 1fr 1fr fractional unit each fractional unit and here also 1fr 1fr you have
it this is the same configuration we had now autoflow says that first once you add this item
one then in which direction you want to add the second item or new incoming item let's say when
autoflow is column it will add it in the column space like two three then once it is done it will
go for four then five and six okay if flow is a row okay it will say that one once I have grid
let's say I'm talking about two by two matrix once I have one flow is a row so I'll fill the
first row then I'll go to the next row is it clear like how grid autoflow works whenever there's a
new incoming item where it should go first filling that it should fill the row then go to the next
row or it should fill the column then it should go to the next column
guys is this point clear like how grid autoflow works
yes to revise right these are the properties that you can apply generally on a grid container
so we have discussed something called as fr which is standing for fractional unit
and each of this fractional unit can be calculated for rows and columns
when you are defining the each column and row width in in terms of fr and this can be calculated
by if you are getting this width width by total fr total column let's say column fr
let's say column fr will give you one fr for column
and then let's say you have height
by total row fr will give you one fr for row right only all these properties
and this can be applied to grid template
column and similarly for this one for the row right and what are the next properties
that we have discussed once we have done this then we went and understood what does repeat function
does and repeat is commonly used repeat is commonly used first we thought like hey repeat
can be only used when you have a constant recurrences like let's say you have a constant
recurrences so we thought that use cases can be different but then we thought what we can make
this both things are variable this one has a variable and this one has a variable
now how in industry standard is like they write down this repeat function and they give like
autofiller or auto fit here two things auto fill or auto fit property
then you go and define this here min max range you give a minimum pixels like most of the times
this minimum range is always in terms of what can be the minimum size of the content in pixel
or rem or em but whereas maximum people try to give in terms of fr terms for the industry standard
okay then we went on to discuss something like justify items
and align items
if you want to move inside a cell if you want to move the content inside the cell left right bottom
top anywhere you can use this property but if you want to move a particular
item inside a container you go for content properties
and grid flow always define in which how the next incoming element should go
in the grid in which cell it should go i hope these points are clear guys i just try to summarize it
uh i hope you got a better understanding about grid now everything will come with practice if
you i would prefer i would ask you to you know revise this lecture once to get the good understanding
write down the properties in your understanding because i'll show why grid is important uh i'll
show after my plea i would ask you to wait for some time in like doubt session where i'll show
the real time debugging how can you debug grid and flexbox both things but coming back to this
one guys there are few there are only less amount of properties for the items okay let's say i have
here a new class called item one what i'll do is that i'll go here i'll select let's say item one
and inside this item one there are only few things now
uh after this promote uh we'll have only 10 minutes then we'll take break okay
only 10 minutes then we'll take break so earlier raja had a question like what if
a particular item want to be in a different position from their existing thing like how
what if item want to move anywhere isn't it like we told that if you want to move all the
items to the center or the top right left we are moving all the items like applying it to the all
the things but if you want to do it individually right you go you can go to the item and you can
say simply justify self once you do justify cells let's say i give start flex start and align self
i say flex start
do you see this guys let's say i make it as a this one also one effort then you will be able to relate
this one raja able to relate this you had this question i remember in chat so you asked me like
how can i make it for one respective one specific item
okay so guys is this clear like if you want to move inside the cell
only one item then you can use something like this property
let's say
uh guys do you need a break or can i continue i see no reactions
so if you need a break because okay let's take the break and come back we'll cover the items part
then we'll go for the practical examples let's do the 10 minutes break okay let me start that
10 minutes timer
can i make it eight minutes guys that would be enough right
right i'll make it eight minutes because i want to cover a few things
few interesting things for you for the like industry standards
let's see you meet you in 10 minutes
you
uh guys is everyone back
uh guys if everyone is back and give me thumbs up thumbs down any reactions guys
i need your attention guys for some time uh okay need your full attention uh so i hope everyone is
back okay so we were can we get started guys can we get started or
uh i know i'll show that i'll show that let's complete this content then i'll show you real
time examples where this grids and flexboxes can be used okay because these are the layouts
like every website that you see in real time right uh you go for any site that you pick it
you pick it any site website you go for scaler.com and so there will be a grid of flexbox being used
okay
okay uh but guys can we get started
so that we were onto the flex like grid items how we can do it so we were discussing two properties
like justify self and align self now we have made like justify self and align self as a flex start
both things and this both items as a sender now this is the same thing this is in this is
the same way how align items and justify items used to work they are also trying to move the
items inside the set but if you want the same like all items to behave in such way then you
have to define it on a container but you want if you want item specific then you can use justify
self property okay to move the container i mean items inside the container is that point clear
guys how does justify in align this self works then we have only two other properties for the
this one let's say one is called as grid row okay what does this thing works how this thing works
is that let's say now i've see that one my column is taking only one unit of space what if i want
this one to take two units of space like did you remember like in table table is also in html tables
right we used to do row a column span and row span does anyone remember that row span and call span
this is the same property that use helps you to span this particular uh each element let's say
i am at the contain item one i'm saying that starting position would be one and please go
through three so what i'm saying is that how this this thing works is like i'm saying that
it goes by grid lines whenever i say grid lines like it says that grid line is one is this one
two is this one and three is this one so i'm saying that this is this starts with starting
and ending line let's say starting line and slash ending line
similarly if i want to expand this on a column level let's say if i want to do a column call span
sort of this then i can say start with one again go till third
is it clear is how the call span and row span works in grid at item level generally you can
give a starting line and ending line i'll exactly show you how you can see the lines now if you see
if you go for any inspect tool right any inspect tool you put on a container you see this grid
once you select the grid you can go into the layouts option and there will be something
like show track sizes area names and the grid lines all it will show now this uh i hope like
i'll remove this one so that you can see this now if you see what's exactly happening
let me make this one itself but what i was trying to say is this visible guys you are able to see
this one lines all the lines one if all the units so when i'm saying it that one first element item
one like if you go for item one css i'm saying that it it will start at the line one indicate
three so this is the line one this is the line two this is the line three so this is how you can
differentiate the other way around is that if you don't want to go in terms of lines let's say then
you have an ability to use something like span like merging the grids exactly like spanning out
each element to multiple columns and multiple rows shant to be more in technical terms
okay so like if you want to spend like let's say you can also use span the same thing if you see
still i'm doing that same thing like i can say that hey start from line one start from line one
span till two elements you can use also the keyword called span if you don't want to give
end line is this clear guys like you can use span or you can define directly end line similarly
what if i want to make this particular item to item two to span to this level let's say i go for
grid row now what would be the starting line for this element let's say if you go here
and see the item two is starting at grid line three right i'll select the three
then i'll go and i'll say the span two okay i'm going for row let's go for column as of
okay it will start from column one and span for two rows
okay so it took the same thing as this one now
let's say i go for grid row also inside grid row i have to say that hey you are starting at line three
and span two
span two
what if you gave the correct number i gave the incorrect number itself shan
now if you see i've said that i'm having three by three matrix
i've gave start from three and span till two two terms right if you see when i did that
if you see this convert this the demography of this particular grid got changed
so if you want to fix this layout go with the description definition of what you have given
in the grid template rows in grid template columns but if you do some mistakes here
or when you are spanning it out or then your layout will be disturbed now if you see go and
see the layout if you say this one and two then three four five and six then seven eight nine
this there is an empty space on the here right you can also fix this fix this what if what
you can say is that hey i'll go and say that item let's say i say that item six i can say dot item six
grid column
right starting at second span two if i fix it this way if you see
it's still if you see this one starting at two i'll give i should be starting at three instead
if you see when i gave it three okay did i let's say i comment this i'll see the issue and fix that
what i'm saying is that this is the line one line two this is minus two you can always see
the lines here also right minus one minus two whatever the lines you are getting here you can
use them and you can span it i say that select the line till minus two and span it till two
let's say i say grid column
let's say i is two minus two and span it still it is doing it from here not
okay it doesn't have the enough space to consume it i guess
but i hope you got the basic idea what the spanning does
okay so grid
let me go back to grid row two starting line would be two let's say when you go for row this
is the starting line and span two it will span around those these two rows yes then here line
two will be used instead of item one huh so it will give errors there is nothing as such error
but it's it's just like how you want to lay out the layer your layers like how you want to show
show your all the fields is that clear shant like if you want to distribute equally you are not
supposed to use grid column or grid row but if you want to span out or if you want to move the
elements you will have the side effects that you have to manage it out
is that clear guys how many of you have any doubts on this like how grid column and rows work
did everyone understood this one how this property works
okay i see two people's hamster cool uh this is what i wanted okay now
okay let's say i start with property one first so
i'm saying that what is the position if you see there are something like each time right
when we say matrix let's say we go to the definition of matrix here
like if you see in the 2d layer grid right if i draw the lines
right this is the line one this is the line two this is the line three this is the line four so
if i'm saying this particular element element item one which is over here i say that grid column
let's say grid column
starting from line one end till three or i say starting from line one span two
i mean spanments consume two lines like line two and line three so it will say that it will move
the item one whatever one is there it will consume whole of this space this space is this point
clear what is the grid column is doing whenever we write this way guys uh i need specifically
thumbs up from the people who gave me thumbs down ankit and tejal
guys is this point clear
okay now when i say grid column
oh sorry grid row
again these lines are also distributed like you'll have specific numbering always you can debug
and check the numbering one of the ways like you can check this numbering like you'll have
minus four minus three minus two or whatever you have or else you can say always let's say
i'm starting from i since this is starting here one and it is going till if you see this is
in the below you had a minus four minus three minus two minus one this is how representation
has been given okay here below if i want to expand till here if i want to expand till here
i'll say grid row whatever row is there right starting from one or let's say minus four
consume it till minus two this is the starting and ending or else you can say minus four
span two
so
clear guys like what i have done in the code here is that when i use grid row
let's say i write down here instead of this one uh in the grid column right in the grid column
uh let's say minus four
so i have written that clearly i hope everyone having better idea now how this spanning works
yes uh still having any doubts do let me know okay always what you can do if you want to go
by the lines right uh you can always wherever grid is rendered you can open inspect tool just
highlight this one and go to the layout section and see all uh tick all this them then you will
if if i don't tick it let's see what all things i'm not able to see many things you won't be able
to see if you see extended lines these are the grid lines that you can see how many lines these
are layout has been divided into so all of this tools will be really helpful to design your layout
like whenever you are doing website right this is only done once on a top level once your layout
is designed internal items you can do anything okay i hope these properties are clear if these
properties are clear yes i would say uh like this is it when it comes to grid part but i want to
show you one of the exact example like exactly like how can you leverage and play around with
that uh let's build one of the layout okay let's build actual one of the layout a general layout
that you see or you generally have been used which had let's say let me write down that layout uh
like firstly uh let's say i have something like layout dot html i use html file uh take some
yeah uh i'm i'm going to show you exact one uh basic uh layout i mean now firstly this is because
i have to introduce one more property then i'll try to show you the exam example that we solved
with flexbox i want to solve that same using grid okay
let's say i have something common header which is like header across
like page you can say page header and let's say i also give the id as page header
okay once you have taken the header let's say you have something like article which is again
a semantic tag which will show the content area let's say this is a content area
again i can give id as a let's say main main article or main content anything that you can
then let's say i have once i have this header and main article i can also have a navbar
i can also have a navbar let's say i have id called nav here or let's say this is a main nav itself
and we can say this is a navbar
and there's something like aside which is like showing the advertisement let's say
on a website
let's say ads so basically and i can give ids as site ads whatever ads you see in a website
particularly okay then let's say you have something like footer and this this is a footer
here so this is how your basic layout looks like right each page let's say
if i go back and write down on the ipad yeah can i show you in a preview nothing will be
you will be able to relate now because we haven't applied anything as of now
you will have a header you will have a footer right you'll have a content area where your
actual content is there then you have some menu section navbar then you have like most of the
sites show ads on the website for the ad revenue right this is how basically you have our top
level elements that you can see on most of the websites or like revenue generating websites
right so now let's see how we can build our layout for this one okay what i'll do is that
uh firstly fixing this style
removing this padding and matching
okay once we fix this then let's go for the body tag apply some basic html
uh i'll give display as a grid but i won't be applying as of now any properties because i want
to give uh let's say a default height could be 100 view height i'm just giving it this one
okay it distributed article just i'm giving that consume all the height not only the top okay
again going to the let's say each part let's say i select header
and also article also aside also let's say nav
then footer covered all for all these things i'll apply common css i'll give just like padding should
be eight pixel and let's say background color just tomato nothing else now
once we have given this let's say i pick it up this ids right i pick up this ids all the page
header and everything let's say page header i'll write down all these ids whatever we have defined
firstly main article
okay then main nav
then you go for site ads
also you have page footer
okay these are the ids we have described inside this thing i'm going to add one property called
grid area this is something new that we haven't discussed yet but i'm just giving it let's say
this is an header and let's say i say grid area i'll say this is a content area let's say content
area similarly i'll say that this main grid area can say menu bar
or menu bar let's say then let's say i say grid area i say ads section
section and i say again grid area footer section
let's say i add a section only header section all these properties
okay you might not be able to see anything as of now the reason now comes the main place
is yeah i'll come to that uncle but let's solve this problem now
there is something that i want to talk about is grid let's say i also give this template columns
and let's say we give columns and also rows template rows now let's say i'm dividing this
into three sections like main content ad section and also menu bar a lot like a side one okay then
what i'll give let's say 20 percent will be aside okay which will be like covering one part of the
thing then one fr will be main frame then let's say 70 pixel can be a ads part i'm just able to
write it because i have built this one guys but i'm i'll explain everything like how i'm able to
assume this one okay then i'll have 80 pixel for the first row then one fr for the middle call a
middle row then 15 percent for the bottom one now till now there is nothing that you can see
also i'll add let's say gap between each of the items as a 10 pixel for the along the column and
row now comes one property which is used to define templates in any
office you go something called as grid grid template areas okay let's say how can you do it
let me pull this also below
here let's say if i go and see what i have defined grid area i'll select the header section
as a header section is something which will be going coming on the top
since i have defined template columns as the three columns i'll give header section as three
times so i'll say that whatever page header is there by default it will consume all the space
next next i'll go and say in the second row i'll go and define the what is my second row looks like
in second row i'll say hey where is my nav bar like menu bar let me get the menu bar
menu section once i have this menu section then i'll go for content section then i'll go for
something called as or what we have defined other thing aside add section
add section
okay menu bar it's a menu section
are you able to relate this guys what i'm matching all the keys grid area keys whatever
key i'm having here defined it i'm matching here like how that my layout should be decided
i'm not writing exactly one one item but i'm using all the things together
now to here i'll use something called as let's say again menu section would be ending part
and let's say these are the footer sections
okay can you see this guys what just we got created very basically simply i haven't done
anything here much complicated it's just that i use one of the magical property called get
grid template areas so what it does is like whatever your main level wrappers are there
whatever your main level wrappers like you build go and see any website you'll have header footer
nav bar content area ads we went on to play like we know that position is there many things are
there all these things are there but but if you want to build a layout if you want to build out
a layout like this one it really fast now the magic thing that i want to show you is this is
flexible this is flexible like if i show how flexible this is because how grid is solving
this magical thing now all the properties we just learned right it helps to solve the minute minute
problems but if you want to create a very basic simple layout see this is this is so flexible if
you go and do it anything these are increasing and decreasing the height and width as per our need
but one thing we want to do is like for mobile devices we are not supposed to have
this way i'll just go and add one media query and i'll try to i'll explain it this one again
whole thing okay let's say what i'll say is that media all and then i'll go and write the condition
as max width
okay let's say i go and say some 600 pixel till 600 pixel apply these properties okay how can i
what can i say this i'll say that go in the whole body inside the whole body grid template areas
inside this grid template areas i'll just define such that in each row in each row let's have
header section only only on the first row then in the second row i'll say that get me the content
section then i'll say that get me the ads
uh what was it ads section then i'll say that a get me the nav uh section
then i'll say that get me something called as footer section
okay i didn't have something called nav uh that's all the menu section
okay now let's see what just just happened did this problem is solved for
smaller screens not completely because we have to fix these properties that we have defined grid
template rows and columns how we want to do we have to we say that when grid template is for single
row single in single column we are defining i'll say grid template columns as simple one fr
fr to consume it whole thing
like in fractional unit then i can go and say in grid template rows again i can give
n number of things that i want like let's say uh 20 pixel then give me something but we don't
exactly need here for the rows whenever you are having mobile view your view is like scrollable
view right you can scroll as much you can you have
so guys do you think till 20 minutes before grid was looking like much difficult to deal with
but do you feel it's difficult when you see this example like if you see this if i'm expanding it
the grid has become changed right just using one property called grid template areas is a
something called which is creating a magic for us in a mobile view it is having all things are
aligned and vertically in like responsive view you are getting this uh the way you want so any
layout go and pick any layout in websites let's say layout examples in html okay
uh you you want to build this is it easy this is header footer sidebar and main content area
easy right you will be able to do with grid template areas straightforward
if you go and do this part header nabba section aside footer aside pretty easy straightforward
right any anything you pick it you try to apply these properties that you have learned even there
are some difficult uh templates and all other properties right item level properties yeah item
level properties those i container level properties this those will help you further whatever
those will help you further whatever properties we have learned those will help you further to
enhance your content like how we want to show it okay only thing only the thing that i've done
here is that i've i've i've generated these values because it's really difficult to do it live
i've just fixed it using it in inspect tool itself i've built it then i'm trying to show that
how can you leverage grid template areas actually and its connection with grid area properties
these are acting as ids and these ids are used in a grid template i guess like how can you load it
is this clear guys this example is clear grid one anyone having any doubts in this
i hope uh no doubts uh if this is clear uh one example guys if you remember uh inside flexbox
right we developed this example in last class
in flexbox we developed this example how many of you remember this
carts one in flexbox right let's see how we can do it in the grid using this example how can we
solve this in the grid okay i have built this one to just show that you can do that same thing
in the grid also and how easy it is because that's also a layout only uh let's say i say
carts dot html now you'll be able to feel like how powerful each item is and what can be used
i'll do one thing i'll copy the html content both are same uh you'll be able to see i'll show both
of things to you
let's say i copy this
okay let's preview this as of now show preview yeah this is working something like that
but this is just an html now let's go apply uh all the properties that you see
okay i'll just apply the properties let me know something that if you feel anything like different
okay so firstly uh i'll give a list of properties that we have applied already in last class
uh even i can pick it from here let's say this all list of properties that if you see
this card image text content button i'm copying this all the css that you see
okay now i've copied that content now what i'll do is that once i have this let's say
i'll also do one of uh we added a box shadow and everything is it no we didn't add it i'll pick
it under the property that we applied here so since it's mixed i won't copy it i'll do
since it's mixed i won't copy it i'll do something like i'll write
uh article article is something attack that we used here uh for the classes
so just adding a border for each card guys uh let's say border one pixel solid
let's say black or let's say uh triple c that same thing that we used also i can pick it up
manually from here itself box shadow also same to these two properties that i needed
okay once i added these are looking like a bit uh on on a liberated stage now let's go
and do the actual styling that where you will do it using
grid display cards now here what i'll do is like i'll say display grid
okay now here i'll say simply grid template columns i'll say something like repeat for me
autofill like you remember autofill right let's say autofit will go for autofit and i'll say min max
uh let's say 200 pixel to 1fr
and i can go and say give me a gap of 10 pixel or let's say 20 pixel
and uh let's say i go and i'll just align the items all the items right uh to something called
a stretch nothing seems to be uh like or else let's say we put it into the center
okay now let's go back and see how flexible is this one okay this is something we have designed
using flexbox i've added only three property for three properties to be specific in grid all the
other uh are like simple basic css okay i open this in the live server again if you see
we can add something like here uh let's say border radius to give that same look
as a eight pixel around each box okay say 12 pixel
now if you see here do you guys feel like same isn't it now i'll show you magic with grid is that
guys it's flexible also flex wrap is working flexible go for mobile screen all will become
scrollable right all are becoming scrollable if a screen size is increasing there is an empty space
there is an empty space coming up why let's say i go and see uh did i make a mistake while writing
auto fit is fine that's why i use auto fill or doesn't auto fit is the right thing to say
because this empty space is coming if i use fill i don't want that empty space i will go with fit
itself okay i hope this example is clear guys you can explore uh this one it's pretty clear so what
i've done is i've built one using flexbox this is also flexible in nature okay so that you whatever
time you have right you will be able to explore and learn both are used for layout one is one
direction the other one is two direction
is this clear is this clear like how this cards is working cards example anyone having any doubts
anyone having any doubts till now so if you don't have doubts i would say i've covered the content
that i have to cover for today's class okay but i'll explain you one of the topic okay
uh give me a second guys
this has deteriorated
my whole layout scalar layout got completely
uh i'm not sure how to fix this i'm starting the doubt session uh because i don't have
other option to see okay so guys i started uh doubt session guys but i want everyone to stay
here i want to uh talk about few things okay that whole layout got struck for me i could not see
anything only one button was available like start out session because we have something new
feature called druva for us uh while expanding i could see some spaces at the end of first row
that you can see it in the flexbox that you can see it in the flexbox if you see here
okay that you can see it in the flexbox example in grids example autofit is applying so it will
expand the card size you can fix that flexbox issue also but you have to explore that how can
you do it so guys i have an announcement that i want to make i've seen few ratings are coming
low so i would request whoever rating me low right i would write ask them to write you know
maybe a feedback like what i can improve or what i can work on if you have challenge writing there
you can ping me directly personally i wouldn't mind i would work on that okay i'm here to learn
one of the skill i'm trying to share what i know as a knowledge i'm trying to learn okay so that
on a lighter note take that on a lighter note but
people who are in class i want to show you few things few amazing things
so hope my screen share is working right hope my screen share is working right
pick any one side guys pick any site pick any random site pick any random site that you like
whatever website you like
youtube guys it would be really difficult to debug youtube
or else i can show that also youtube fine no worries let's go to youtube
okay let's say i explore this one now i remove this one okay this is how youtube is rendering
now what i want to show you here is that this is the whole html youtube has written right
okay market me dot in i'll i'll talk about the tank but so shanth has suggested me youtube
so guys this is a html that youtube has written right for this rendering website now let's say i
go and select here the flex box if you see can you see this flex when i'm hovering over it
when i'm hovering over it hovering over it if you see the whole page is highlighted you see
this whole page is highlighted so they have built this layout using flex box this is the something
we have learned if i go and click it see they applied something called display as flex and they
gave something flex basis property also and if you want to see actual properties while of what
applied right you can go to the computer you can say flex places you have they have given flex crow
flex string they have defined all these properties
okay you can play around with them let's say i i go and say uh let's say i go and say whatever
flex is there now i say this i was a block no when i say block let's say this element actually what
all this element is targeting that i have to see to show you the changes let's say instead of block
let's say we say in line do you see any changes guys that are being applied
let's remove this display itself
so you what i what i mean to say is that you can always see this this container wherever
these cards are rendering this whole cards rendering are on this flex box but if another
thing you can do is like you can click on this okay flex box editor if you want to play around
you don't know what property to apply on any website you can open this and let's say i have
this i do something like this like column reverse if you can you see anything here all the videos
gone gone away right let's say i select this one column not working if i select row by default
this youtube i used flex direction as a row is that point clear like how can you see
what what they have applied or what properties they are playing around with let's say if i
use flex wrap this will only work when i am reducing increasing size let's say align content
justify content let's say we make it into the center or left align because they their content
is completely fixed and their spaces are filled you might not be able to see this property being
applied okay but you can see using this flex direction there are some some properties are
you know all the properties they applied those are gone so what i want to say you is that you
know go and open each existing websites right this is also another thing that is applying
at the same part like if i if i remove this let's say i deselect i select this one
this is the container you will be able to see even the part right when you click on this
on which area this flex box is applied you will be able to see that thing getting highlighted also
so you can go and see you can learn actually let's say they are having flex direction as column
if i remove it let's say everything is gone if i align this items let's say align items are
on center i say that flex start nothing changes because the space is completely consumed
or flex end right so you can play around with all of these things let's say the column reverse
so what i am saying is that you can go and explore these sort of things any other website guys you
want to pick it up where here i am able to see only flex because i want to show you grid
any other website guys choose other websites i'll show you grid also youtube has used
flexbox everywhere it is a flexbox so do you understand the importance of these things guys
what we have learned just now what we have just learned how important is this stuff is
see the header is also fixed header is also fixed using flexbox all the items are in
row what if i change into column
okay i change into column this has become into that what we say a menu button in a mobile view
like you open this you will be able to see like menu button in mobile view this is how centered
right so all you can also play around with this one let's say this is a column i want to make
it reverse you see this button came here on the right side youtube came on right side compared
to the whatever its order is so this is actual live website you can see that this is the
website where i'm trying to play around i'm trying to learn from there okay let's go someone
suggested me apple website apple.com this is the one of the website where you have too many
transformations and too cool to be actually you know let's say if i go for a but i'll show you
this particular thing directly firstly let's say you go and open here here also everywhere
see yeah we got the grid guys can you see this grid
apple is using grid layout 2d layout and whole content is selected if i select this grid
now they say they are using grid gap okay they are passing some i mean this is from javascript
perspective guys they are using some variable they are passing real-time values now they are
also using something called grid template areas they have used grid template columns so if we
know all of these values right what we have just learned all of these things at least these are
you are able to relate you know because everything nothing should be new to you because we are
concluding the part of html and css now everything that you see on the screen like this could be
like a html element or a tag or the css property you should be able to relate it if you are not
able to relate or anything you have doubt let me know i'll explain that explore we'll explore that
okay now let's say we remove this display grid so this part right whatever they are doing on the top
this is where it is fluctuating if you see if i am playing around with that
on and off and you can go and see in the computed area what all things they have applied actually
here display grid is there then they have applied font weight grid template areas none
but they have given template grid template columns this is coming from a variable value okay
and line height is there this is something we have used already row gap is there row gap is
coming from again like whatever we have defined here gap that is coming from variable
okay that's coming from js again z index right so what i was saying is that again there is a
new section for this section now if you see when i highlighted this guys can you see this
yellow line somewhere between a low line here
now they have a gap of some let's say 10 pixel and this is a 1fr and this is the 1fr
so they converted a website into two columns isn't it
this is what we intuition we get right let's say let's see what they have done here we are
not able to see this one because see the columns and this values right if you see
the column value is two so if you say these are we got two columns now going back again
like i have clicked here this is a real time value two columns repeat two columns of one of
one fr each right if you go and say grid grid gap give a 12 pixel of gap okay
so go and apply and even for firstly for to lay show this right you have to select this
one grid lines and if you don't select this one you won't be able to see these yellow lines or
anything okay uh let's say i also select this one there are too many things guys flexbox all
things you can select and explore this i want you to explore this all these things okay till the
properties whatever i'm introducing right you have free time open inspect tool try to debar
choose your favorite website someone also suggested me hotstar website i might not
have logged in into this one let's say
they have also built i would say only disney symbol will be coming out let's say only this one right
got logged out login let's say this is a how this has been aligned okay this is a small layout
right this is a small uh no no reason so this i just let's discuss on css5 but this is a small
layout right small layout let's say how the small layout is built okay uh please let's go here and
select this whole content okay here if i selected whole content this content is built using flex
if i select this flex let's go below and see how they have said that hey display is flex
i'm using column and i'm using some dynamic value 40 rem now they have used something called as rem
value then also if you see this box is bit curved this box is bit curved because they have given
some radius like eight pixel also they have given some background color this is coming like hash
whatever hash code we many hash codes we have seen right now what if i change this one into row
do you see this
got changed now all the layouts in this world are built using this two only guys flex box
and grid that's why i am spending more time explaining you the importance
you go into any website if you know these two layouts if you know this tool
specific specifically flexbox because grid is used one time to set out the whole layout
flexbox will be used to layout all the small items small things that you design
okay and flexbox is completely easy use that flex froggy revise it put a sheet on your
like wall keep doing it because this is going to be really important you go for
any machine coding around this will be important
js okay we'll talk about that upendra in future like if you don't mind why we need getting
values from the js because those are calculation specific they calculate if this viewport is there
pass on this value pass on this value they do some sort of logic but i'll talk on that
specifically okay most of the sites will send the dynamic values to this one okay see box
box sizing is for hotstar they applied it yeah i'll talk on that i'll talk on that like what is the
like syntax right firstly whenever you are going for like you know type of cases
in naming css class okay so if you see basically one thing i would suggest
not this one not this one but have anyone heard this bem convention
this is what we generally is followed at a like you know industry standard whenever
i'll give you this link i'll actually tag this link in today's class bem convention is a
convention like how like you go and say that i want to define for each html element a class name
how would i define it there's a certain standard now bem talks about something like block element
modified okay so block element block is like what type of block it is like then you go for element
underscore depth then modifier modifier is like uh let me give you an example i would want you to
go through this one let's say button right uh let me show you actually examples i wish i should
i can show you my pr how i used to write if you see this uh this is a block called nav then i'm
using a lease item lease item is a like element underscore underscore then if you have modifier
you can use again underscore underscore and add new thing that you want to do but this is how you
do it once you this first thing is common category then you go for sub common category like lab nav
dot underscore lease item both are same then you add something unique like let's say underscore
item one to be specific okay but i would want everyone to go through this article guys uh
if you are going to the industry standard anywhere writing uh naming convention thanks for asking
this uh i'll put it here in the link let's say i'll give all the links also i'll push the code
guys uh stay in the call i'll give this uh let's say naming convention for css
there are too many standards guys naming conventions uh for css we follow them uh but
if you go for uh like constants how they few people follow camel case few people follow snake
case camel case is somewhere starting from a small letter and then all the words that you append
will be capital okay same you have many other things uh let's say i have other websites
uh something that i want to link this is auto fill versus auto fit
i try to explain this at at most simple way it's just a difference between the space
okay then one of the most important article that you have to revise is this one whole thing grid
uh when i say revise it just to click keep your concepts clear use these two classes talk uh this
one uh at most guys like keep revising you face any challenge you're not able to understand drop
in we'll discuss in the whatsapp chat uh what is figma figma is something a tool used by like we
are using vs code or any other thing like figma is a tool that is used by ux uh ux designers they
uh ux designers they design what have to be designed like you are not as a developer you
are not responsible to build this that hey this product will look like this they will give you
this thing they they want this device logout layout to be this way on your figma tool you
will try to replicate by writing the code on it is that clear it's just a tool like it's a website
where they design all the websites like ux designers do that and they share with you because
you are not supposed to uh uh design it they'll design it you are going to code it you are a
developer you're not a designer that's a difference it's for a designers you
uh let me push this code guys let's let's go to readme.file also once
we have covered okay class five we covered something called as flexbox
uh then we discussed uh media query then we uh repeated uh revised uh but that's fine uh
that's fine uh class six we discussed grid
and layout example
custom layouts then uh also we built cards example here cards example with flex
uh
here we have built using cards example with grid okay
grid commit minus nm uh class six nodes
uh
okay dummy side yeah open the CSS so Ankit had his built his own websites he needed some suggestions
uh can we go ahead and say any other time Ankit like I'm like we are overshooted much long actually
two hours 35 minutes others let me explore this uh but I can if you want my real time suggestions
actual suggestions I would need some time okay this looks cool design is cool uh that's my first
impression uh so you have your own company is it
uh this is for what like this is your organization like this is what market.me.in
like uh okay uh let's say page source
use table use something like table padding spotters
uh okay some some are like taken but taken from wordpress okay
any website you build right chrome understands only HTML and CSS I told you mother languages
they take only that other thing understand it you have to give it that part so you can always
explore like you have media queries uh you have let's say
let's say you have many classes defined here if you see here header main layout
if I show go and show you right even if you picked it when you fixed it from there right
see do you see flex boxes everywhere
okay great but do you see flex boxes everywhere that same thing even if you want to build it you
got stuck you design it by your own saying the seeing this one you got stuck load your website
open the flex box apply the same properties using your HTML and CSS you will be still able to do it
it's like reverse debugging reverse engineering okay for each thing like you can pick this div
hedge feed site what this do what is this is doing right you can go and do it everything
you have applied position relative and many things are there but looking cool you can if you build
this right using the properties that we I would say build this using react uh even with the HTML
CSS which doesn't have any behavior this will give you a really great experience uh dealing
with this HTML and CSS okay because what I can say is like this layout is like uh you know
boxes everywhere behind the scenes this gives me that already agreed like feeling
but uh good one it would be a really great exercise actually see every container in a
flex itself like it's a flex box this particular container or anything if you go on a top level
if you go on a top level let's say top level uh this is a body item
if I remove this body shadow see your websites look odd now
one element is doing the magic like gradient uh adding the all the colors and background images
because this is this is made cool completely cool using background image
and repeat this background properties had uh helped you a lot and
what cool one here one should prepare this sort of sites anyone like uh once we learn JS right
I'll give you really one cool task one can implement that one uh
so hello guys if you don't have doubts can we close the session I see many people got dropped
in real time how we'll get the project requirement I'm from a non-coding
background so I just wish to chant it's it's simple right um as we just uh discussed
this that we have a figma sort of tool where they give you that hey I need let's say
uh they'll give you a task like or a user story they'll ask you to build this thing out so you'll
have a layout first once you do HTML and CSS part then you will write uh all the like uh
logics that you have to do it like login again or closing let's say if I click on a close
there is some action going on right once I closed it it redirected me to the home page
right so all those behaviors you have to handle that's one of the example actually
but it would be really great like to go and uh which kind of project should we practice so
I'll teach you a few projects I'll teach you a few projects uh and I'll also help you out
if you are building your own project okay think of it uh basically we'll be building on HTML
CSS JavaScript once we learn that uh we'll be building one till we complete JavaScript
we'll be learning two projects then on react we'll have one project then on full stack we'll
have one project four projects I'll also share that simple portfolio project right code after
next class I'll share it I'll upload here only where you can go and refer it and you can improve
uh you can improve this one completely uh the CSS that we I have written or what we have done it
okay that portfolio project initially I've shown you right uh I think if that url is cache
yeah if this url is cache right so this particular thing that I'll share with the code base
I wish I wish you design it on your own guys okay this would be really basic if you go and do it
this is a menu bar this is one section second section third section four section
four section
okay uh guys any if you do there must be a foot or two yeah uh
I mean yeah there should be a foot or two but you can add it you can customize it as much you can
like for a beginner level uh I mean I'm actually what I feel like I'm introducing too many
complicated things also because uh for a for last batch I didn't go into that depth initial
classes because it would be too heavy for people to take it uh sometimes uh but you can always
customize this and get like whatever you want to add there too many things better can be done
right one of the best cool websites that I feel like you can explore uh like if you want to see
3d sites
if you go and see uh 3d websites
so
I mean not this uh but they are showing how can you build it
let's say 20 awesome websites so if you want to really stand out right
if you want to really stand out as a fresher or anyone
this is the cool one let's say what this they are doing chipperlay.ai
now let's say if I'm scrolling it I'm guys I'm scrolling it below now if you see
when I'm scrolling it I'm getting something new I'm just scrolling it below
these are like transformation CSS these are like advanced really advanced like how can you deal with
this cool looking cool right
apple at apple uh you won't be seeing it at a top level top level website has really simple
but if you go for let's say mac and you open uh macbook pro let's say macbook pro
uh and now if you scroll if see the 3d uh evaluation and how images are changing
see now they got something new right I'm scrolling it below so there are stories coming in
I'll slowly slowly I'll show you like what they are doing behind the scenes okay
if you really scroll speed right if you see all the images were not loaded if I really scroll
speed there is something going on because this the images they use right are so heavy so heavy in
nature let's say I okay they're pre-loaded is it once I click it let's say I go to some other
product iPad shop iPad buy iPad uh okay I got three calls which fetched me documents okay
all things are being returned uh preview see I got some documents html documents response
would be directly html they gave me but the cool thing would be guys uh let's say I select
like uh one thing would be they have scripts too many JavaScript is written here
but let's say I search here image
will come to this
you pick this
they have deployed on their uh see they haven't written description about this
if you go and do some security issues like performance right let's say I go and do
a performance here for profiling for this side because this thing might be
uh they have done built it using uh different uh teams like this shop slash iPad
they this team might be a completely different okay
so you can see actually uh paint time 6.2 minutes this is really quick this is first time paint
you can go and explore like for different different uh actually I'll explain the step
by step guys like uh don't you know take it as heavy uh like what is exactly happening
and why what are the screenshots and what we are what I'm showing everything because
and what we are what I'm showing everything because as a front end developer right when
you grow over the when you grow down the lane you have to understand this things if you see out of
all the time 10.4 or 10.8 milliseconds were actually taken by uh parsing that html all other
tasks were really small okay right the other biggest task was recalculate the styles whenever
you are using styles and overriding it that was a maximum second thing okay so you can see uh
what all things are taking time just doing by profiling you'll get it
if you are fixing this side of issues now these sort of issues because I fixed one of the great
issue last year which was based on js heap uh this heap storage we got memory leak in our application
that was one of the hell of the tasks because
yeah I'll I'll try to uh just throw light on them but because those are really in depth chance like
we need a specific classes for them but I'll give as much as knowledge and reading documents
that you can go and explore on yes uh if the content for uh you know flexbox grade and display
position properties display properties have covered inline block inline block none flexbox
great keep revising them most important okay then so hello guys then we'll close the session my
ears are also painting holding this microphone
uh
then I'll stop the class if I stay here I'll keep on speaking something
have a good night uh
young kids will have till like we have still three months to explore we can keep on discussing many
things okay uh okay I'll do that open I'll check that
I didn't go through this uh okay thank you uncle okay good night guys hope you saw all the uh you
know uh assignments and problems also and I'll see if there is a tool where you can practice CSS
grid I can give you one uh and we'll enjoy all the time guys all the all these four months right
right we'll learn a lot we'll don't panic anywhere like if you're facing channel and come back let's
discuss because I'm picking all the international main long websites we are applying we are seeing
them uh those are the same things that we are learning of the are being applied in there
nothing new just with practice you are going to build them with just with some practice
guys good night take care thank you all
you